Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
So today's דף Daf is כ"ח. Kaf-Chet.
What is today's דף? Daf?
Today's דף Daf is כ"ח. Kaf-Chet. We start from the bottom of
כ"ז Kaf-Zayin עמוד ב׳. Amud Bet. We're in the middle of talking
about basically what happens when nowadays when you don't have a fixed
value for a field, how do you determine it? And it's interesting
because you also could have talked about a שדה מקנה, Sde Mikneh,
which the תורה Torah doesn't assign a fixed value, but there anyway
it's not so clear. There by the שדה מקנה Sde Mikneh could
be that it is a fixed value, it's just proportional to the
years, it's just that what happens at the יובל Yovel is different.
It's not so clear in the פסוקים. Pesukim. Anyway nowadays what happens
when there's no fixed value? יובל Yovel does, there is no fixed
value, יובל Yovel doesn't affect anything, a sale is a sale, a
הקדש Hekdesh is a הקדש, Hekdesh, there still is a possibility to
redeem it from הקדש Hekdesh if it's in the hands of הקדש.
Hekdesh. How do you determine the market value? So
one second. So there the משנה Mishnah says there really are two
possibilities. One is that you get an assessment and you determine the
market value, and it seems like from the משנה Mishnah that that's
always a fallback position. But there also seems to be that
the first take is to do an auction, but sounds like a
silent auction, in order to hopefully get a price that's higher than
the standard market value. And within that context you give the owner,
you not only give the owner the first choice, you basically make
the owner participate because A, there's a מצווה Mitzvah for him to
do it, B, if nobody else wants the field at least somebody
will buy it, C, once he's in the auction he'll have to
add a fifth. So you make the owner participate and then what
we've been seeing is pretty unusual rules about what happens in terms
of who wins because somebody could make a higher base bid but
we would award it to the owner because through his fifth we'll
actually get a higher final amount which means that the owner really
has to know the rules of the game before going in because
he has to realize that whatever base bid he gets it might,
yes, but especially the owner because whatever base bid he makes it
might be pushed up against his knowledge and he should be prepared
for that possibility going in. Yes, Michael?
So it seems from the משנה Mishnah there's still a גזבר, Gizbar,
there's still a בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, it's just that there's no
יובל. Yovel.
Yes, and we said that yesterday, let me just repeat that, that
תוספות Tosafot says if there's no בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash then you
would just redeem it on a פרוטה Perutah because there's no monetary
interest, you're just removing the קדושה. Kedusha. So the scenario is there
is a בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, there's no יובל, Yovel,
which was the story the entire time of the Second בית המקדש.
Beit Hamikdash. תוספות Tosafot makes that point. Yes.
But nowadays would you do the same thing or...
No, that's what I just said. תוספות Tosafot points out that nowadays
since there's no financial interest that the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash has
because it's not using the money anyway, the whole point is just
to remove the קדושה Kedusha and you would just redeem it on
a
פרוטה.
Perutah. Even nowadays people are just so far removed from being מקדיש
Makdish things, like there's no בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, what are you
doing? No one knows הקדש Hekdesh anymore, you just
can't be that serious anyway. That's an interesting question,
which is, on the one hand, it's a type of דברים שבלב,
Devarim Shebalev, you say the right word. On the other hand, as
we know, and as I said at the very beginning of this
מסכת, Masechet, when you deal with issues of הפלאה, Hafla'ah, your inner
state of mind is pretty significant.
So it's an interesting question if
you'd say nowadays people don't even know what they mean when they're
saying that they're מקדיש Makdish it, but maybe it depends if you've
learned in ישיבה Yeshiva or learned the דף יומי Daf Yomi or
not. So that's an interesting question. Let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
But it seems like this is a bizarre case where it would
be much easier to lay out principles. If you just said that
you look at the owner's bid as if it were twenty percent
higher
then that would cover everything.
No, because remember the משנה Mishnah has a more bizarre principle which
is that if somebody says twenty-one and he says twenty, so you
take the higher bid and you award it to the owner and
you force him to go by the higher bid, so it hasn't
said the principle by concrete...
But he has to pay the entire... Right, right, he has to
pay the
fifth of the entire...
Exactly, exactly. I want to say something about that exactly because basically
the idea of going, normally law, if you look at תורה, Torah,
we're about to get to פרשת משפטים, Parshat Mishpatim, is case law.
It's like in its earlier stages it's articulated as case law, as
concrete cases. Abstraction, and actually concrete cases are pretty good because abstraction
can be too abstract and you really don't, there's really an importance
or balance between abstraction and concrete cases. Anyway, so in the תורה
Torah it's basically almost all case law. In the משנה Mishnah it's
almost all case law. Every now and then you have a זה
כלל, Zeh Kelal, right, which is a move of abstraction and then
the גמרא Gemara always says זה כלל
לאתויי מאי? Zeh Kelal L'atuyei Mai? But it might not be that
זה כלל Zeh Kelal is coming to include something, it might be
זה כלל Zeh Kelal is basically saying like we start with concrete
but now let's actually take a step back and try to abstract.
And as you get further in the Amoraitic period, you have more
and more abstraction and less and less the proportion shifts more
and more. One of these days we'll read the
גמרא, Gemara, go ahead.
Yeah. Let's say, so the owner, whatever it is, you know, is
pushed up to a potential 25 right there, right? So let's say
the owner is in addition to his fifth. So let's say he
says, you know, I really can't afford 30 שקל. shekel. I mean,
can he back out without penalty or is he really forced to
do it?
No, it sounds like he's forced. ממשכנין אותו. mamashknin oto. You're stuck.
Yeah. I mean, this is a... no, but all the cases seem
to be ממשכנין. mamashknin. We sort of force you. Now what happens
if the guy has absolutely no assets to pay for it, you
know, will we then go to the next bidder or will we
have that as an outstanding debt? I don't know, that's an interesting
question. Presumably, הקדש Hekdesh will do what's in its best financial interest
in those cases, but I don't know. Let's take a look now
at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so now we are
about seven lines down in the wide lines, with the two dots.
אמר אחד הרי הוא שלי. Amar echad harei hu sheli. So basically
somebody said
20, the owner said 20, and somebody else said 25. So what
we're doing, we're saying, and this is particularly strange, we say, okay,
this guy said 25, the owner said 20, but if we take
his 20, it'll become a 25. So, okay, but the other guy
still said a higher base price. But no, what we're going to
do is we're going to award it to the owner. Why? Maybe
because of the general preference to the owner, or maybe because once
we award it to the owner, we're going to apply now that
principle, which is, okay, the owner wants it, but the base price
is set at the higher price. So now it becomes the other
guy's 25 plus the five of the owner and gets to be
30. And that's what the משנה Mishnah says. The גמרא Gemara is
not so happy with this. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר אחד הרי הוא
שלי. Amar echad harei hu sheli. So the גמרא Gemara says, בעשרים
וחמש והבעלים בשלושים. b'esrim v'chamesh v'habalim b'shloshim. So
this guy said 25, so the owner gets it and he has
to pay 30 because this guy's 25 plus his extra five. לימא
הבעלים, Leima habalim, why can't at least in that case the owner
say, אשתכח גברא בחריקי? ishtakach gavra b'chariki?
I have a man in my standing in my place, in my
stead. So בחריקי, b'chariki, חריקין charikin is an interesting Aramaic word, but
it basically means somebody who's a substitute for me. So this guy
said 25, what are you doing coming to me now? This guy
says exactly the same as I would say if you added my
fifth. Okay? So take him. So to say we're still going to
take you because it's going to mean, you know, we're going to
force you into more money, but at the initial level, I'm saying
25, he's saying 25, there's no basis to go to me instead
of him. The גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא—now, Gemara again, you
would think that that's the חידוש chiddush of the משנה, Mishnah, that
we're still going to try to get as much money as we
can, but the גמרא Gemara actually says that's a good argument, and
if that were really the case, we would go to the guy
who said 25, we would not put it on the owner. So
what's the case in the משנה? Mishnah? So it makes the case
in the משנה Mishnah a special case. דאמר בעלים דינר. d'amar balim
dinar. That, ah,
you didn't really say 20, you said 20 and a דינר. dinar.
A דינר dinar is like a quarter of a שקל. shekel. So
you said 20 and a bit, 20 and a bit, 20 and
a quarter. Okay, so then you say 20 and a quarter, oh,
now plus the fifth, now it's more than 25, and now you
actually win. Okay, which takes away the entire חידוש, chiddush, then we're
just back to the old point, which is that once you add
your fifth, if you're higher, we give it to you. So the
גמרא Gemara says, וליתני דינר, v'litnei dinar, so say you said 20
and a דינר. dinar. ולא דק, v'lo dak, it's not being precise.
Meaning, it says 20, it's rounding, but it's a little funny to
say it's not being precise. The whole
purpose only applies because he said and a little bit. The גמרא
Gemara says, though, are we not going to be precise? והקתני אם
רצו הבעלים ליתן שלושים ואחד ודינר הבעלים קודמין. v'hakatani im ratzu habalim
litein shloshim v'echad v'dinar habalim kodmin.
At the end of the משנה, Mishnah, which we'll explain in a
minute, it says the owners have the option in a different case
to say 31 and a דינר. dinar. So you see the משנה
Mishnah does mention דינר, dinar, so you can't say it only mentions
שקלים. shekels. אלא אמר רבא דאמרו בעלים פרוטה. Ela amar Rava d'amru
balim pruta. Okay,
so they say 20 and a penny. Okay, and the משנה Mishnah
isn't talking about pennies. ולא דק, v'lo dak, it's not mentioning it.
So again, it's very strange because the whole הלכה halakha hinges on
him saying and a penny and we're saying it's not bothering to
mention it. So the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is we
actually put it on the owner even when it's 25 and 25,
but it's interesting, the גמרא Gemara draws the line there, says, no,
that we're not prepared to say. If he said 20, he said
25, and in the end they're saying the same, then you have
no right to force the owner into that situation and it's only
when the owner said 20 and a penny. Okay, so that's that
case in the משנה. Mishnah.
Now what if the owner wanted it? Yeah, and they were even.
That's an interesting question if the owner said... yeah,
no, well, that depends how then you read the end of the
משנה, Mishnah, whether he has an option, the owner has an option
to up his bid, which we'll get to. Okay, so on the
one hand you're right, the end of the משנה Mishnah sounds like
the owner has an option to up his bid. On the other
hand, that's interesting, you know, he wanted it and then he was
willing to go all the way
up to the 30 based on what the משנה Mishnah says. Maybe,
you know, maybe then it would give him at least that option,
I don't know, that's an interesting question. Okay. כשהם מוסיפים חומש על
עילוין. Ksheheim mosifim chomesh al iluyon. And what about 21 and then
25?
We're going to get to that. כשהם מוסיפים חומש על עילוין. Ksheheim
mosifim chomesh al iluyon. Now, the fifth is only based, although we
force the owner to accept the other guy's higher assessment, the חומש
chomesh is only based on his bid. אמר רבי יהודה לא שנו
אלא שלא נישום הקדש בשלושה. Amar Rabbi Yehuda lo shanu ela shelo
nishom hekdesh b'shlosha. That's only true... True that his fifth is based
on his bid and not the other guy's bid, only if הקדש
hekdesh did not have the field assessed, independently assessed with three. רש"י
Rashi says the חידוש chiddush of three is that the general rule
is that הקדש hekdesh will assess things with ten. We learned that
out in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. But here if it was at least a
minimal assessment with three, then that will actually
bind the owner. So meaning what רב פפא Rav Papa told us
is the other guy's higher bid can bind the owner if for
some reason we're awarding it to the owner anyway.
But here we're going but at least the fifth is based on
the owner's bid. Here we're going to say not only that, but
the fifth will be based if there's an independent assessment, the fifth
will be based on that. So here would be the scenario: the
owner said 20, this other guy said I don't know 22, and
then there was an independent assessment of 22. It seems the way
at least רש"י Rashi frames it that the independent assessment has to
sort of has to be the same as the higher bid, so
it reinforces the higher bid. Yeah I know, so רש"י Rashi doesn't
talk about what that case would be and the גמרא Gemara doesn't
anyway. But let's assume that's true. So then we follow the same
rule where the owner's 20 becomes 25, he wins it, but because
there was a higher bid 22, he has to have that as
his base. And now we're going to say if that 22 was
reinforced by an independent assessment, now his fifth has to be based
on that 22 as well. So it's not just the fifth of
the 20, it's the fifth of his 22. Okay that's what רב
חסדא Rav Chisda had in mind. What happens if the independent assessment
was even higher than the 22? Would the owner be bound by
that? Or would it at least be enough to make him have
to go by the 22 for his fifth? I don't know. Right,
I don't know the answer to any of those. And if he
says 10, and they
appraise it at 100, right?
No, so he needs to pay a fifth of 100? No.
So again, רש"י Rashi says this is only
when the assessment reinforces the other guy's higher bid. Now what's not
discussed in the משנה Mishnah is, right,
the משנה Mishnah gives scenarios where it sounds like these bids are
higher than the market price. Let's say we go out and we
get a market price and then we open it for bids and
all of the bids are lower than the market price. Okay, are
we the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash bound by that? Presumably not. Presumably
we will wait until there's a person who's willing to buy it
at market price. Okay, it's sort of like what's that thing that
they have on eBay,
a minimum bid?
Something like that.
Standard in auctions.
Okay, that's implicit I think in the משנה Mishnah but it's not
spelled out. Anyway, let's keep on going. אבל נישום הקדש בשלשה, Aval
nishom hekdesh bi-shlosha,
מוסיפין. mosifin. But if הקדש hekdesh had an assessment of three, then
he would have to yeah I guess once you make that point
it's also saying that this independent assessment is not only reinforcing the
other guy's bid, but it's well see if it were just setting
a minimum then we would have thrown out the owner's bid. It's
hard to exactly get all the rules here. Anyway, okay, but if
it had this independent assessment then מוסיפין, mosifin, then he wins it
even though he came in lower, and his fifth has to be
based on this other guy's bid which was reinforced by the independent
assessment. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly: בית שמאי
אומרים מוסיפין ובית הלל אומרים אין מוסיפין. Beit Shammai omerim mosifin u-Beit
Hillel omerim ein mosifin. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that you actually
have to add his fifth based on the higher bid, and בית
הלל Beit Hillel says you don't. So the גמרא Gemara asks: היכי
דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי דלא נישום, Ei delo nishom,
if there's no independent assessment, מאי טעמא דבית שמאי? mai ta'ama de-Beit
Shammai? What's the reason of בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? Which is a
little bizarre question. All these rules here seem relatively arbitrary, so who
says maybe you do have the fifth on based on the other
guy's since the other guy's bid is the basis is your base
assessment anyway becomes your base assessment anyway. אלא דנישום, Ela de-nishom, it
must be that it was assessed. And therefore that's now we understand
why בית שמאי Beit Shammai is saying that you have to add
your fifth based on that. So the גמרא Gemara says: one minute,
like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, למימרא דרב חסדא דאמר כבית שמאי? le-meimra
de-Rav Chisda de-amar ke-Beit Shammai? You're saying רב חסדא Rav Chisda is
only like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? Since when do we ever go
like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? So the גמרא Gemara says: לעולם דלא
נישום, Le-olam delo nishom, it wasn't assessed. So then and even so,
ובית שמאי מחמירין, u-Beit Shammai machmirin, and even so בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is strict and says the fifth is based not just on
the owner's bid, but it's actually based on the higher bid. אי
בעית אימא, Ei bayit eima, or you could say, לעולם דנישום, le-olam
de-nishom, it was assessed, ואיפוך, ve-eiphach, and maybe the positions are reversed
from how they were recorded.
בית שמאי אומרים אין מוסיף. Beit Shammai omerim ein mosif. בית שמאי
Beit Shammai would say that you don't add when it was assessed,
ובית הלל אומרים מוסיף, u-Beit Hillel omerim mosif, and בית הלל Beit
Hillel says you add. At least רב חסדא Rav Chisda is saying
like בית הלל. Beit Hillel. So the גמרא Gemara says: if that's
true, בית שמאי Beit Shammai is being lenient, תני ליה גבי קולי
בית שמאי וחומרי בית הלל? tanei lei gabei kulei Beit Shammai ve-chumrei
Beit Hillel? It should have been in the list of things that
בית שמאי Beit Shammai is lenient, if בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
you don't and בית הלל Beit Hillel says you do. אלא לעולם
דלא נישום. Ela le-olam delo nishom. The only way to explain this
ברייתא Braita is, keep it the way it is, that it has
not been assessed, ובית שמאי מחמירין. u-Beit Shammai machmirin. And even so
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says the fifth is based on the guy
on the higher bid, not on the owner's bid. Okay, in the
end therefore the way we're interpreting this, this ברייתא Braita didn't support
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, because this ברייתא Braita is talking about it
wasn't assessed. So in the end רב חסדא Rav Chisda is still
making an assertion which isn't supported, isn't contradicted, that when the other
person's bid is reinforced by an assessment then and now we're putting
it on the owner, the owner's fifth has to be based on
that. Last case of the משנה: Mishnah: אמר אחד הרי היא שלי
בעשרים ושש. Amar echad harei hi sheli be-esrim ve-shesh. Now this was
the case which is interesting. The משנה Mishnah said one guy said
26, the owner said 26. So that should have been obvious, right?
So the owner's 20 becomes a 25, the other guy's is 26.
So obviously give it 26 and sorry, but the משנה Mishnah says
if the owner... want, they can now do thirty-one and a bit.
Now what's thirty-one and a bit? Thirty-one and a bit is twenty-six
as a base plus a fifth, because a fifth of that twenty-six
will get you which is really a quarter will get you five
and a bit. So that's thirty-one and a bit. Actually it gets
you five and a dinar, which is exactly what the משנה Mishna
says, okay? Because four dinars in a shekel. So it sounds like
from the משנה Mishna that if somebody outbid the owner, the owner
gets one last option, which makes sense, right? מצוה דבעלים Mitzva d'ba'alim
and so on. And if the owner's going to win, he's going
to win. So he gets one last option to outbid the guy
based on a base bid. That's what the משנה Mishna sounds like.
This guy said twenty-six, we're going to award it to him, but
we make one last turn back to the owner and say 'would
you like a chance to outbid twenty-six? Or at least or to
at least meet the bid of twenty-six? And if you meet the
bid then we'll give it to you.' That's what the משנה Mishna
sounds like. What?
אם רצו הבעלים אם רצו הבעלים בשלושים ואחד ודינר. Im ratzu haba'alim,
im ratzu haba'alim b'shloshim v'echad v'dinar.
Okay, so this is given to them on all of those, right?
No, no, no, that's on the last case of twenty-six where he
was outbid. Okay, so that's what it sounds like. But let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara does not read
it that there's a second that there's a last option, okay? The
גמרא Gemara reads it that it's all based on your first bid
and therefore it has a problem with this last rule of the
משנה. Mishna. So let's take a look. גמרא Gemara says like this:
רצו אין לא רצו לא. Ratzu in lo ratzu lo. So it's
only if you want, if it's not if he doesn't want, he
doesn't have to bid thirty-one and a dinar. Why? אמרי Amri because
he can say 'look, עשא גברא בחריקי, asa gavra b'charikei, you have
a guy to take my place. I said twenty which at most
is twenty-five, he said twenty-six. Here's the guy you want to go
to.' So he doesn't have to, so obviously we can award it
to this other guy. That's obvious. But why can, if it's can
the owner if he wants, you know, why can the owner get
it at a higher price? ודינר מאי עבידתיה? V'dinar mai avidtei? So
then what is this dinar? So where is that coming from? It's
clear what it's coming from because the twenty-six plus a fifth is
a dinar but the owner never said twenty-six, the owner said twenty.
Okay, meaning it seems like the גמרא Gemara is considering the following
possibility: that the owner could say 'if I the owner wanted to,
I'm sticking my bid doesn't change, my bid is still twenty, so
my fifth is still five, right?' So it sounds like the גמרא
Gemara says it could have made sense that when now we're saying
that the owner has the option of going meeting the guy and
going up to twenty-six. But then it should have just been thirty-one.
Why is it thirty-one and a bit? The only way you get
thirty-one and a bit is if you allow the owner, you know,
to actually, as if it were, change his initial bid. So let's
take a look. ודינר מאי עבידתיה? V'dinar mai avidtei? אמר רב ששת
הכי קאמר. Amar Rav Sheshet hachi ka'amar. Here's how you read it:
אם רצו בעלים מעיקרא מדי חשבון המגיע לאחד ועשרים. Im ratzu ba'alim
me'ikara midei cheshbon hamagia l'echad v'esrim. If the owners had originally given
a higher bid that would have translated into thirty-one and a bit,
which means if they originally would have said
twenty-six, then ודינר. v'dinar. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? How would that have
been possible? דאמר בעשרים ואחד. D'amar b'esrim v'echad. I'm sorry, not that
they would have said
twenty-six, they would have said twenty-one. How oh, right, because if they
would have said twenty-one, right, right. If they would have said twenty-one,
what would have happened? They would have said twenty-one. The other guy
said twenty-six. So who do we award it to? The owner because
his twenty-one becomes twenty-six and a dinar, right? So once it becomes
twenty-six and a dinar, so now we award it to the owner.
But now we use the base of the other guy's twenty-six, so
it's twenty-six plus the five and a dinar gets you thirty-one and
a bit. What?
We already have that.
I know. So it's not really a bigger חידוש. chidush. According to
them, once again, it's just reiterating the earlier principle because it said
מעיקרא. me'ikara. The חידוש chidush of the משנה Mishna seems to be
not like 'oh had you made a different initial bid'. The חידוש
chidush of the משנה Mishna seems to be like you have a
choice now to change your bid. היכי דמי דאמר בעשרים ואחד הבעלים
קודמין ואם לאו אמר לו הגעתיך. Heichi dami d'amar b'esrim v'echad haba'alim
kodmin v'im lav amar lo higaticha. But if they didn't have a
higher bid as initially, if it was just a twenty bid, then
the twenty-six wins. So the גמרא Gemara takes the case where it
sounds like the owner has a last chance. It says no, no,
no. It means if the owner's initial bid was different which was
translated into thirty-one and a bit. But if the owner had initial
bid of twenty, then we give it to the twenty-six guy. Okay,
but again the simple sense of the משנה Mishna is we allow
at least we turn to the owner and say 'you know what?
Would you like to up your bid? If you would up, I
think I said it wrong before, because a fifth of twenty-six is
not thirty-one and a bit. A fifth it's a fifth based on
twenty-one. But anyway, regardless, it sounds like the משנה Mishna we go
back to the owner and we say 'would you like, you know,
you have one last chance. If you up your bid to twenty-one,
then based on the whole math, it'll turn into a thirty-one and
a bit and you'll be able to win. Would you like to
do that?' But the גמרא Gemara says no, no, no, you don't
have a chance now. You have to have made that higher bid
earlier.
Okay. So the twenty-one...
a fifth of twenty-one is five and a dinar, right. And then
you get your thirty-one and a bit. So the point is that
while you that's clearly what's going on in the משנה, Mishna, that
the owner has a chance to say twenty-one, the משנה Mishna sounds
like it means you have a chance now to say twenty-one. You
know, you give the owner one last shot. Whereas the גמרא Gemara
added this key word מעיקרא. me'ikara. What?
That only that you don't he doesn't have a last shot, it's
only if he had said that higher bid earlier. Initially. Okay. All
right. Let's take a look now at the משנה. Mishna. At what?
We're still applying the rule that like if
you're bound by the other guy's higher bid.
Yeah. And and a full shekel, only time it's it's a dinar.
I'm trying to understand when there'd be like a little, little teeny
bit.
When the... Anything that would have- anyway. דינר denar is definitely what
it happened with. By the way, the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says
on the conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara, he quotes תוספות Tosafos in
קכ"ו, Kuf Chaf Vav, ט"ז, Tes Zayin, תמה מאי רבותיה. Tamei Mai
Revuteih. That's what we're saying. So what's the whole point of saying
this? We already said that principle. So again, the real חידוש chiddush
of the משנה Mishnah seems to be you have one last shot,
but that keyword מעיקרא me'ikara in the גמרא Gemara sort of takes
that back. Let's take a look now at the next משנה Mishnah
top of כ"ח עמוד א'. Kaf Ches Amud Aleph.
מחרימין Machrimin now. We go from, as I said, we are moving
our way to the end of בחוקותי. Bechukosai. Now, not only that,
we're really dealing with cases about being מקדיש makdish things to בדק
הבית. Bedek HaBayis. Okay. So, one thing was ערכין, Erchin, the other
thing here was שדה אחוזה Sedei Achuzah in the past, and שדה
מקנה. Sedei Miknah. We also mentioned, what do you call it? We
also mentioned הבית habayis which is in the פרשה parsha here at
the end of בחוקותי. Bechukosai. And then we're talking about חרם. cherem.
Now חרם cherem is not as explicit. It's mentioned more in passing
here.
It says like this. It
says,
it says, when it talked about the שדה, sadeh, it says, one
minute, והיתה השדה בצאתו ביובל קדש לה' כשדה החרם לכהן תהיה אחזתו.
Vehaysa hasadeh betzeiso bayovel kodesh l'Hashem kisedei hacherem lakohein tihyeh achuzaso. I
was מקדיש makdish my field, David here bought it, what happens when
it comes to יובל? Yovel? It goes back to הקדש, hekdesh, right?
Because I didn't redeem it. And who gets it? The כהן kohein
gets it. And within that context of the כהן kohein getting it,
it says כשדה החרם, kisedei hacherem, like a field that was made
חרם. cherem. Okay, so and
in קרח Korach where it lists the gifts to the כהנים, kohanim,
it says כל חרם בישראל לך יהיה. kol cherem b'Yisrael lecha yihiyeh.
Every חרם cherem goes to you. So apparently there was one way
of sanctifying something to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, or actually which
translated into כהנים, kohanim, by saying this is חרם. cherem. חרם Cherem
also means like a ban, actually sometimes you use חרם, cherem, you
know when it's by יהושע Yehoshua and עי Ai and everything was
put under the ban, meaning nobody could benefit from it. So it's
interesting that חרם cherem had different meanings based on context. And sometimes
putting someone in חרם. cherem. Sometimes it says כל חרם קדש קדשים
הוא לה'. kol cherem kodesh kodashim hu l'Hashem. So that's going to
be a discussion in the גמרא, Gemara, does it go to בדק
הבית, Bedek HaBayis, does it go to the כהן, kohein, but at
least some פסוקים pesukim say כל חרם לך יהיה kol cherem lecha
yihiyeh to the כהן. kohein. Here it says כשדה החרם. kisedei hacherem.
So now we're going to move to talking about what happens if
somebody says this is חרם. cherem. Okay, does it go to a
כהן? kohein? What? No, to an object. This object is חרם. cherem.
What we're going to discuss, can you do it on certain people?
A, what's the status of the object and so on, and B,
who does it go to, etc. So now we are moving to
discuss חרם. cherem. Let's take a look at the משנה mishnah of
putting something on a ban. Okay. מחרימין אדם מצאנו ומבקרו ומעבדיו, Machrimin
adam mitzono umibekaro umiavadav, somebody can put under... could say חרם cherem
on some of his flock. The מ' mem is very key as
we'll see. Some of his cattle, some of his servants, משפחותיו, mishpachotav,
some of his female servants הכנענים hakenaanim ומשדה אחוזתו, umisdeh achuzaso, some
of his inherited fields. ואם החרים את כולם, V'im hecherim es kulam,
but if he said they're all of them are חרם. cherem. Now
all, does it go by each type or does it go all
his property together? The גמרא Gemara is going to say it goes
by each type. If you try to make חרם cherem of an
entire... of an entire genre, that's the wrong word, whatever,
category of property, all of my fields are חרם, cherem, all of
my slaves are חרם, cherem, then אינם מוחרמין, einam muchramin, דברי רבי
אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it does not
take effect. חרם Cherem only works on part of your property. Why?
It's interesting, because you would think that if your word transfers a
metaphysical principle, you know, metaphysical state, that who cares, all or part?
But nevertheless, it's only on part. Now, we have something similar to
that by, I would say תרומה. terumah. תרומה Terumah is, you know,
you can make תרומה, terumah, you have a flexible amount, how much
to give for תרומה, terumah, it could be one seed and it
could be everything minus one seed. But for it to be תרומה,
terumah, it has to be... you have to be תרומה terumah from,
it has to be removed from something else, which means that there
are שיריים, shirayim, something left over. So you do have this idea
where you can sanctify but only in the context where there's something
left over. But there it's conceptually different, because there the idea is
you have all this produce, you are giving an offering from the
produce, that's how it's phrased. חרם Cherem is basically just like writing
a check to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's not like, you
know, everything I took in and I'm taking some of it and
giving. But that at least is what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is
saying. It can only be some and not all. We're going to
learn it from a פסוק pasuk in the... in a minute. Let's
take a look. דברי רבי אליעזר, Divrei Rabbi Eliezer, that's what
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. אמר רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Amar Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah, so רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, a different רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says
מה אם לגבוה אין אדם רשאי להחרים כל נכסיו, mah im l'gavoha
ein adam rashai lehachrim kol nechasav, when it comes to even the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we don't allow you to give over all
your property. So he's going to learn like a more sort of
moral message here or general מוסר mussar message, על אחת כמה וכמה
שאדם חס על נכסיו, al achas kamah v'chamah she'adam chas al nechasav,
or maybe דרך ארץ derech eretz message I should say, על אחת
כמה וכמה שאדם חס על נכסיו, al achas kamah v'chamah she'adam chas
al nechasav, how much more so that you should be, you know,
careful with your own money. Like, don't put all of your money
in a wild investment. Or not only that, don't put all of
your money even to give it away to צדקה, tzedaka, to the
עניים. aniyim. Okay, you have to... it's sort of like, you know,
what is it? חייך וחיי אחיך חייך קודמין. chayecha v'chayei achicha chayecha
kodmin. It's very nice that you want to be a religious individual
and give all this stuff to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, give
all this stuff to צדקה, tzedaka, but... take care of your own
interests as well, and you have to make sure that you're leaving
yourself some property to survive on. I should, by the way, point
out that this might be in a it's not clear to me
this but anyway in the early period of the church there were
definitely which is right around the time of the משנה Mishnah there
were definite you know powerful stories about people that gave all their
property to the church and became poor and joined up to become
followers you know of the church. And the גמרא Gemara is very
clear that that is not you know want that is not desired.
You know, you continue to help yourself, and not only help yourself,
help the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and help the עניים Aniyim if
you keep some money for yourself and remain a productive individual. Don't
become one of the עניים Aniyim and remain a productive individual in
society. Okay, so that is anyway, that's the the sort of larger
message that רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה
Rabbi
Elazar
ben Azaryah is taking out of this. Yes. Is this in contrast
to some examples we had in previous about sanctifying all your property?
Or did we just had a week
ago or so when somebody was so poor that he had to
get money in order to get borrowed something? So there somebody was
giving...
Right. So actually it's a good point which is is that A,
there's a question is it allowed? B, there's a question if it's
effective. If I give away all my property to the poor, it's
still effective even if the rabbis told me I shouldn't have done
it. Okay, by חרם, Cherem, it actually doesn't take effect. But that's
when I'm using the technical term חרם. Cherem. If I just said
I'm מקדיש Makdish all of my property to the בדק הבית Bedek
HaBayit and then I can. So this is not an absolute principle,
it might be a general principle of how I should act, but
in terms of it actually limiting the effect, that's only in the
narrow case of חרם. Cherem.
But what was it you said about הקדש? Hekdesh?
Right, that's what I just said. So the limit is only the
fact that the effect is limited, that it doesn't take effect is
only in the case of using the term חרם. Cherem. That's what
you just said, right?
There's a difference I don't understand I guess between הקדש...
Hekdesh... Well it's just yeah it's just a different well we're going
to see there's a question what do you do with חרם? Cherem?
So again, it obviously has different type of a resonance because you
could use חרם Cherem to make stuff the term used חרם Cherem
when it sort of says they conquered this city and they were
מחרים Machrim it, you know, יהושע Yehoshua והעי, ve-HaAi, it was חרם
Cherem of the פה Peh and it was off limits. So there's
obviously a different religious resonance. How exactly it translates, does that mean
it goes to בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, כהנים Kohanim or whatever, but
you know it has...
For your principle why isn't it better to give everything so you
become poor?
Right. So that might be a principle of behavior but not that
it doesn't take effect. If you write away if you write a
check to all your money to the poor, it does take effect
even if you shouldn't have done that. And the same by being
מקדיש. Makdish. The only place it doesn't take effect is if you
use the term חרם. Cherem.
So let's say the חרם Cherem is a negative term that you
are removing it from yourself whereas הקדש Hekdesh is a positive term
that you are granting it to somebody else to the הקדש.
Hekdesh. So חרם Cherem is I'm saying it's off-limits.
So that would kind of be in line with what you said,
you know, don't don't deny negative also don't deny
yourself to
to try to benefit somebody else but don't be you know...
That's interesting. I mean still the case of the עניים Aniyim we
still say you shouldn't give all your property to the עניים Aniyim
but your point still is at least with the הקדש Hekdesh the
difference might be that if the focus is on the on the
recipient it's not as it's not as problematic but if the focus
is on you divesting yourself of it then don't be such a
פרומי Frumie that you're going to divest yourself of all your property.
That's a very nice explanation. Okay, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי? Minani milei? Where do these come from?
דתנו רבנן: De-Tanu Rabbanan: we taught: מכל אשר לו, Mikol Asher Lo,
from all that is his. So this is in
this is in again in what do you call it? This very
end as I said of בחוקתי. Bechukotai. So I read the earlier
פסוק pasuk of שדה חרם. Sdei Cherem. I should have but here
at the very end of בחוקתי Bechukotai we have the following פסוק:
pasuk: כל חרם אשר יחרם מן האדם לא יפדה. Kol Cherem Asher
Yochoram Min HaAdam Lo Yipadeh. I'm sorry, I started too early. אך
כל חרם אשר יחרים איש להשם, Ach Kol Cherem Asher Yacharim Ish
LaShem, every חרם Cherem that a person would be מחרים Machrim to
God, מכל אשר לו, Mikol Asher Lo, from anything that he has,
מאדם ובהמה ומשדה אחוזתו, MeAdam u-vehema u-misdei achuzato, whether
person, animal, animal like a slave, animal or field, לא ימכר ולא
יגאל, Lo yimachair velo yigael, is not sold or redeemed. כל חרם
קודש קדשים הוא להשם, Kol Cherem Kodesh Kodashim Hu LaShem, it's holy
of holies to God. So what does it mean? It's not redeemed,
holy of holies to God. So so if they can't sell it
what are they going to do with it? And what does it
mean קודש קדשים הוא להשם? Kodesh Kodashim Hu LaShem? It's just going
to have it sitting around and not doing anything? So the פסוק
pasuk is very unclear and the גמרא Gemara will therefore try to
explain what the halakhic implications are but we're now going to focus
on the first part of it which is
מכל אשר לו, Mikol Asher Lo, מאדם, MeAdam, ובהמה, u-vehema, etc., which
is from things that you own but not everything that you own.
But again notice how what we're doing is we are working our
way through the end of בחוקתי, Bechukotai, right we had ערכין Arachin
and then we had שדה אחוזה Sdei Achuza and now we're at
the very end of בחוקתי Bechukotai which is חרם. Cherem. Yes.
So קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim for the kosher animals they would presumably
become עולות? Olot?
Yeah, but if you read the פסוק pasuk literally. But let's see
what the גמרא Gemara does. Okay. So let's take a look. Because
the גמרא Gemara says like this, דתנו רבנן: De-Tanu Rabbanan: מכל אשר
לו, Mikol Asher Lo, if you מחרים Machrim from everything you have,
ולא כל אשר לו, velo kol asher lo, not everything, just from
everything. מאדם, MeAdam, from the humans, meaning slaves, ולא כל אדם, velo
kol adam, not all the slaves. מבהמה. MiBehema.
It says ובהמה. u-behema.
I know, so if you look at the side it says בקרא
כתיב bikra ketiv ובהמה. u-behema. And actually later the גמרא Gemara is
going to do a different דרשה derasha from בהמה. behema. So some
actually take out these words because גמרא Gemara later's going to do
a different דרשה derasha from בהמה. behema. Okay, ולא כל בהמה, velo
col behema, משדה אחוזה misedeh achuza from the שדה אחוזה, sdeh achuza,
ולא כל שדה אחוזה, velo col sdeh achuza, not all of the
field. יכול לא יחרים ואם החרים יהיו מוחרמים, yachol lo yachrim v'im
hichrim yei muchramim, right, maybe it's just a principle of don't do
it, but if you did it, it actually takes effect. תלמוד לומר
אך, talmud lomar ach, אך ach however, meaning it doesn't always take
effect, if you actually do too much, do everything, it will not
take effect. דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's what רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says. Now that's interesting because דברי רבי אליעזר, divrei Rabbi
Eliezer, which is also in the משנה, Mishnah, means you're assuming that
there's somebody who argues, but we never find anybody at least that
argues, so presumably it's an accepted rule. אמר אלעזר בן עזריה amar
Elazar ben Azaryah said רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah,
מה אם לגבוה אין אדם משלח להחרים כל נכסיו, mah im l'gavoh
ein adam m'shaleach l'hachrim col nechasav, if you can't even do
it for גבוה, Gavoh, all the more so that a person should
be protective of his own property in general. Now again, רש"י Rashi
says it means even if you want to give it to the
עניים, ani'im, which if that's the context, not meaning just don't invest
all of your property all of your money in a hot stock
or something like that, you know, but if that's the point about
the עניים, ani'im, then it's an interesting קל וחומר kal v'chomer because
it's an interesting question of a hierarchy, whether we think that it
is of greater value to give your money to the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash or of greater value to give your money to the
צדקה tzedakah to עניים. ani'im. I should point out interestingly that although
in the vernacular when we talk about צדקה, tzedakah, it incorporates every
type of religious gift of the money, whether I'm giving it to
my kids' Jewish day school or whether I'm giving it to my
שול shul or the מקוה mikvah or whether I'm giving it to
the עניים, ani'im,
actually, besides the use of the term צדקה, tzedakah, there's really only
an explicit מצוה mitzvah in the תורה Torah to give to עניים.
ani'im. There's not a מצוה mitzvah to give it to—and we're about
to be פרשת תרומה, Parshas Terumah, right, when there was a collection
then there was a מצוה mitzvah to give to the building of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and obviously, you know, if you wanted
to frame it, all of that type of money goes under תלמוד
תורה, Talmud Torah, גמילות חסדים, Gemilus Chasadim, I mean there's a lot
of types of things but in terms of like an actual מצוה,
mitzvah, you know, that's focused primarily on the עניים. ani'im. So anyway,
it is interesting, although again, sort of in the religious cultural way
we have sort of collected all of them and seen that all
of those are equivalent ways of using your money. Given that it's
interesting that the way רש"י Rashi is going to read this and
that's eventually the way the גמרא's Gemara going to read it as
well, that it really is sort of saying that oh if you
can't give it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash how much more
so you can't give it all to the עניים. ani'im. You know,
we might have thought that the hierarchy would have been different, you
know, maybe בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you shouldn't give all of, בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash has plenty of money anyway, but the עניים ani'im
maybe you should. So again, if that's the hierarchy, it's interesting.
Just bringing the פסוק, pasuk, if the—it's a phenomenon like גמרא Gemara
דרשנ'ינג darshening plain, it's כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u-ferat u-klal, right, it's
כל מן kol min and it does a פרט prat and it
does another כלל, klal, right, it's כל מן. kol min. So you
know so anything eliminated, like for instance say שמלה. simlah. Okay, that's
an interesting question
for those things not, yeah I don't know, I did not look
at the מדרש הלכה Midrash Halakha on the פסוק pasuk so maybe
there is also a צו tzu to that. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes on וצריכא u'tzricha and it has to say all
of these cases: מאדם ומשדה אחוזה, me'adam u'misedeh achuza, it cuts off
מכל אשר לו micol asher lo from everything you have, now presumably
that means your chattel because then later it's going to talk about
sort of you know slaves and land. So this is understood as
being chattel, that's again by the way maybe it's why it's not
a כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-ferat u-klal because גמרא Gemara assumes it
means מטלטלין metaltelin chattel.
הוה אמינא כל דאית ליה ליחרם, hava amina col d'is lei lachrim,
maybe—maybe don't do all of your
property, אבל מן אחד ליחרמיה כולה, aval min echad lachrim lei kulei,
but if it's one category then you can do it all. חס
רחמנא מאדם ולא כל אדם, has rachmana me'adam velo col adam, no
you can't even do a complete category, even all your slaves is
not acceptable, only some of your
slaves.
If it said מאדם me'adam ולא סגי—ולא סגי בלא עבדא, עבודה, avodah,
meaning that you can't get around without, you can't manage without slaves.
You need people to do the work in a pre-industrial society, okay,
and with what, you know, in a
labor—in agriculture which is highly labor intensive, I mean that's the reason
that the institution of slave lasted so long,
right, because there at least the perception was it would be impossible
to have a go of it without slaves. אבל שדה, aval sadeh,
סגי ליה בדיסטורון, sagi lei b'distoron, but maybe—so we won't let you
sanctify all your slaves, but fields maybe yes, why, what are you
going to do with slaves if you don't have fields? Because you
could be a sharecropper, you could work somebody else's field. So maybe
we would let you sanctify all your fields. ואי אשמעינן הני תרתי,
v'ei ashmuni hani tarti, had it just said these two, you can't
do all your slaves and all your fields, משום דהא חיותו והא
חיותו, mishum d'ha chayuso v'ha chayuso, both of those are central for
your livelihood. You can't make a go of it in an agricultural
society without fields and without slaves. אבל מטלטלין, metaltelin, but when it
comes to chattel, so you know, your TV Wait so is it
the whole השמעינן? Hashmeinan? I thought he even said you can't do
all your slaves and all your fields משום דהכא חיותו והכא חיותו.
mishum dehacha chiyuso vehacha chiyuso. Both of those are central for your
livelihood. You can't make a go of it in an agricultural society
without fields and without slaves. אבל מטלטלין, Aval metaltalin, but when it
comes but when it comes to chattel, so you know, your TVs
and whatever, all those things, לא שמעינן כלהו? lo shamainan kulhu? Maybe
that you could sanctify all your chattel because you could still make
a go of things if you have slaves and land? Because it's
assuming מכל מטלטליו mikol metaltalav means chattel. Okay. So therefore it tells
you even that not. צריכי, tzrichi, you need to tell me all
those three things. That it can't be any full category. Now the
question is how do you define full category? Right? The משנה mishna
says, you know, מצונו ומבקרו, mitzoino umibakaro, like it seems to be
a very narrow definition of full that sheep and cattle are defined
separately.
בהמה, behemah, they
I know, but a male and female I know, but it says
מבהמה. mibehemah. So if I did all of my sheep you would
say that's not all my בהמה behemah because I have cows. Right?
So female and male slaves seem to be separate. So you know
it seems that we are going beyond the פסוק pasuk and defining
categories pretty narrowly because we really and which is a way of
really limiting don't go overboard. Okay. So now the גמרא gemara says
like this, בהמה למה לי, behemah lamah li, what's בהמה behemah coming
to do?
כדתניא, kidetanya, like we taught in ברייתא, braita, יכול יחרים אדם בנו
ובתו ועבדו ושפחתו העברים ושדה מקנתו? yachol yachrim adam beno uvito veavdo
veshifchato haivrim usedeh miknato? Maybe this is actually going to be the
next משנה. mishna. Maybe you could sanctify things that you don't fully
own? Where are things you don't fully own? Well let's take a
look. Your
children, עבדו ושפחתו העברי, avdo veshifchato haivri, Hebrew slaves, right? Because Hebrew
slaves are not owned as property. They basically are like indentured servants
for six years but they're not owned as actual outright as property.
ושדה מקנתו usedeh miknato or a purchased field during the time of
the יובל yovel because then you only have a functional lease on
it. You don't fully own a field a purchased field at the
time of יובל. yovel. Maybe you could be מחרים machrim those? One
minute. Right? תלמוד לומר בהמה. talmud lomar behemah. No, it has to
be like a בהמה. behemah. מה בהמה יש לו רשות למכור אף
כל שיש לו רשות למכור. mah behemah yesh lo reshus limkor af
kol sheyesh lo reshus limkor. Only things that you could really sell.
Now of course again with the purchased field you could sell you
know the remainder of the usage until the יובל yovel but
again what but
you don't have full and outright title to the property. Now I
want to point out a difference about the שדה אחוזה sedeh achuza
because if I would have had a שדה מקנתו sedeh miknato I
could be מקדיש makdish it, we just discussed that before. Right? המקדיש
שדה מקנתו hamakdish sedeh miknato and then you know and then it's
sold for the remainder of the years whatever and then it goes
back to the owner. So it's specifically a law in חרם. cherem.
חרם cherem has these parameters. It can't be all of a certain
type of property. It also has to be something that you can
fully give you own fully and give over fully. So שדה מקנה
sedeh mikne although you could be מקדיש makdish and you're מקדיש makdish
the years until the יובל yovel you cannot be מחרים. machrim. You
had a question Charlie? Yiftach. Yeah well oh please. Not now. Okay
so the גמרא gemara says like this.
So now but that's essentially what Michael's question except here we're asking
the one halachic example of that. So the גמרא gemara says והלא,
vahalo, Rifka pay attention.
והלא בתו קטנה יש לו רשות למכור? vahalo bito ketana yesh lo
reshus limkor? How about his underage daughter? He can sell her as
a slave.
So יכול יחרים ממנה? yachol yachrim mimena? Maybe he should be able
to be מחרים? machrim? תלמוד לומר בהמה. talmud lomar behemah. מה בהמה
יש לו רשות למכור לעולם, mah behemah yesh lo reshus limkor leolam,
not just an act of sale but it's actually a permanent act
of sale. It's really full title and you fully transfer. אף כל
שיש לו רשות למכור לעולם. af kol sheyesh lo reshus limkor leolam.
It has to be something you can fully sell. Why not בתו
קטנה? bito ketana? Because once she becomes בת מצוה bas mitzvah or
whatever she is free or the owner has to decide to marry
her. Now I'll take your point in a minute. I just want
to say there seems to actually have been though a little sharper
point here because even when the father sells his daughter he's selling
her as an אמה עבריה amah ivriya and we already said an
אמה עבריה, amah ivriya, you know, it's not owned as property. So
it's not just that he cannot dictate her status for life but
it's actually that you know so it's not just the question of
the duration. It's that even the sale is effectively a type of
an indentured servitude but not an actual ownership as property. That's the
difference between אמה עבריה, amah ivriya, עבד עברי eved ivri on the
one hand and עבד כנעני eved kenaani on the other. So it's
interesting the גמרא gemara sort of framed it that way about the
לעולם leolam because it seems to be a more basic a more
basic reason. Rifka.
And why does he even raise that issue because we already said
not your son, not your daughter, not your עבד ושפחה?
eved veshifcha?
So why why would they
even?
Yeah so that's more or less what I just you know what
I said which is that since the degree to which you know
son and daughter could mean the son and daughter that's at the
daughter that's beyond the age of בת מצוה. bas mitzvah. But to
the degree that you couldn't sell your daughter it's not any different
than עבד ושפחה. eved veshifcha.
But here they're saying is it because that she's even less?
I don't know. I don't think so. I mean the גמרא gemara
never considers that and I mean the classic אמה עבריה amah ivriya
is when a father sells his daughter. That is what an אמה
עבריה amah ivriya is.
But here they've already ruled?
I know, I really don't know, but you can't say it's saying
that selling your daughter is worse or different than אמה עבריה. amah
ivriya. Selling your daughter is אמה עבריה. amah ivriya. But that is
what אמה עבריה amah ivriya is. So you're right. It's redundant.
Or maybe when she's three years old she's you're selling her she
may she may be worth less than an אמה עבריה. amah ivriya.
No but her but her... Not maybe when she's three years old.
She, you're selling her. She may, she may be worth less than
an אמה עבריה. amah Ivriyah.
No, but her, but her, her status, her halakhic status. What is
the אמה עבריה amah Ivriyah that's talked about halakhically?
I think as you might sell her, she's useful, she can work.
I understand, but I'm saying
the daughter is less?
No, no, but we're not communicating here. Because daughter isn't less than
אמה עבריה. amah Ivriyah. הלכה Halakha when a father sells his daughter,
what does she become? An אמה עבריה. amah Ivriyah. When הלכה Halakha
talks about an אמה עבריה, amah Ivriyah, it's talking about somebody, they
are the exact same case. Talking about a father who sold his
daughter. I don't know the answer to that, okay, but I'm just
telling you, there is no sold daughter that is not an אמה
עבריה amah Ivriyah and there's no אמה עבריה amah Ivriyah that's not
a sold daughter. So they're in the same case and I don't
know why it's treating it separately.
You're trying to be so smart here. What about an עבד נרצע?
eved Nirtzah? It says עבד לעולם. eved le-olam. Can you מחרים mahrim
him?
So again, first of all, that's not לעולם, le-olam, that's עולמו של
יובל, olamo shel Yovel, for one. But again, that's why I think
it's strange the emphasis which goes back to the point on the
עולם olam because the real point is, it's indentured servitude, it is
not sale. And therefore, why did it have to emphasize the לעולם
le-olam and treat the daughter separately? So again, I don't know. אמר
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Amar Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, אם לגבוה לא
חס על ממונן של רשעים. im lagavo'ah lo chas al mamonam shel
rasha'im. Now we go to sort of expanding this. Oh, so you
shouldn't do other things as well. Give all your money away. היינו
תנא קמא? Hainu Tanna Kamma? Isn't that the same as what the
first תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said? No, because the first one is
telling you הלכה Halakha in חרם, cherem, he's taking it and teaching
you a broader principle. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that somehow the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar would agree with this
larger. איכא בינייהו דרבי אילעא. Ikka beynaihu de-Rabbi Illa. The question is
how they would apply רבי אילעא. Rabbi Illa. What does רבי אילעא
Rabbi Illa say? דאמר רבי אילעא, De-amar Rabbi Illa, באושא התקינו, be-Usha
hitkinu, in אושא Usha they
established, המבזבז אל יבזבז יותר מחומש, hamvazvez al yevazvez yoter mechomesh, if
somebody wants to
squander, it's a funny phrase, but here it really does mean in
the context of צדקה tzedakah very clearly. So here's where the גמרא
Gemara is translating this statement to be about צדקה. tzedakah. If you
want to give away all your money, you should not do more
than twenty percent, like two מעשר. maaser. That's the maximum. The standard
is one מעשר, maaser, maybe, although that whole idea about מעשר כספים
maaser kesafim is a post-גמרא, Gemara, although on the other hand, it's
also in the חומש, Chumash, by אברהם Avraham and whatever, but as
a הלכה. halakha. But anyway, maybe there's a religious sort of ideal
of מעשר כספים, maaser kesafim, double that is the top, more than
that is not desired. Okay. Well, that's an interesting question to ask
nowadays, what about like the mega rich? Like if Bill Gates wanted
to give away, which he does give away a lot of money,
if he wanted to give away fifty percent, would we say no,
no, no, that's a חרם? cherem? No.
So that's an interesting question which is discussed. But anyway,
מעשה באחד שביקש לבזבז יותר מחומש, ma'aseh be-echad she-bikeish levazvez yoter mechomesh,
ולא הניחו לו חבריו. velo hinichu lo chaveirav. Somebody wanted to give
away more than a fifth and his friends would not allow him.
ומנו, U-manu, who are the friends that stopped him? רבי יהושע. Rabbi
Yehoshua. ואמרי לה, Ve-amreilah, others say רבי ישובב, Rabbi Yeshovav, רבי ישובב
Rabbi Yeshovav was the one who wanted to give away more than
a fifth, ולא הניח לו חברו, velo hiniach lo chaveiro, and his
friend didn't allow him. ומנו, U-manu, who was his friend? רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. Okay now, what does it mean they're debating this principle
of רבי אילעא? Rabbi Illa? The simple sense I would say is,
is that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar isn't talking about other things, he's
only talking about חרם. cherem. You know, maybe he doesn't have a
position about the other question. And the other one's no, no, no,
by other things as well we have to apply it and it
shouldn't be all. By the way there's a big jump from saying
it shouldn't be all to it should only be up to twenty
percent. But anyway, that's one way of reading it, that one is
broadening the conversation and the other is narrow. רש''י Rashi doesn't read
it that way. רש''י Rashi actually reads
that because רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah emphasized you
should be חס על נכסיו, chas al nechasav, he was talking about
like a low, like like you should really protect your money, and
that would be רבי אילעא Rabbi Illa who says not more than
twenty percent. Twenty percent. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar just said don't give
it all to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So if you transferred
that to צדקה, tzedakah, don't give it all to צדקה, tzedakah, but
certainly it could be thirty percent, fifty percent, eighty percent, who knows
what. Okay, so as that's the way רש''י Rashi understands it that
they really are, not just he's not talking about רבי אילעא, Rabbi
Illa, but they're debating whether twenty percent is the appropriate maximum or
not. All right, but there by the way, nobody says it doesn't
take effect if you actually went ahead and did it. Now we
go on, now to more laws of חרם, cherem, and this משנה
Mishna is really the,
effectively the ברייתא Beraisa we quoted before. המחרים בנו ובתו, Hamachrim beno
uvito, somebody tries to be מחרים machrim his
children, עבדו ושפחתו העברים, avdo veshifchato haivriyim, or his male and female
slaves, Hebrew slaves, so none of these are things that you
own, ושדה מקנתו, u-sedei miknato, or a purchased field, which you only
effectively have a lease not
ownership, אין מוחרמין. ein muchramin. It does not take effect. שאין אדם
מחרים דבר שאינו שלו. She'ein adam machrim davar she'eino shelo. You can't
do something that is not yours. Again, that's the דרשה Drasha on
the פסוק Pasuk is everything else, but the underlying principle guiding us
is these things are not yours. But again, by the way, שדה
מקנה sdei miknah I want to repeat, you can be מקדיש makdish
because then you're really just מקדיש makdish the next twenty years or
thirty years of use, but by חרם cherem it has to be
real outright ownership.
What if a fetus and עובר ubar are considered part of the
mother? You can't do that, own that.
Yeah, it's not a monetary ownership. Okay. Now,
although there are גמרות, Gemaras, whatever, that might raise that issue. Anyway,
I don't want to get
into that. Okay. הכהנים והלוים אין מחרימין, Hakohanim vehaLeviyim ein machrimim, דברי
רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. Now הכהנים Kohanim and הלוים Leviyim cannot
be מחרימין, machrimim, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. We'll see
why in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי שמעון אומר הכהנים הם מחרימים שהחרמים
שלהן. Rabbi Shimon omer Kohanim hein machrimim shehacharamin shelahen. Now we're starting
to talk what happens to חרם. cherem. The חרם cherem goes to
כהנים Kohanim is what we're, he's assuming. We're going to have a
more explicit discussion about that in the next משנה. Mishna. He says
look, the חרם cherem goes to כהנים Kohanim anyway, then obviously a
כהן Kohen being מחרים machrim is still, because you get to keep
it. Now the גמרא Gemara says which כהנים Kohanim does it go
to? Maybe it goes to other כהנים, Kohanim, maybe it goes to
the כהנים Kohanim who happen to be working that week that I
was מחרים. machrim. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say that
no, it goes to the כהן Kohen I want to give it
to. So, since it goes to the כהן Kohen I want to
give it to, what point,
it's meaningless for me to be מחרים machrim because I can just
as well keep it. Now of course you could say, well who
knows, maybe I want to give it to a different כהן Kohen
and maybe I have my friend the כהן Kohen who doesn't like
to accept charity, who knows what, but if it's חרם, cherem, maybe
then you know it's not an outright like you know, just צדקה,
tzedaka, maybe he'll, who knows what my logic is? But for whatever
reason he says, since anyway you're entitled to take it back is
how you have to read it even if you don't want to,
then it's it's not meaningful to do an act of חרם. cherem.
That he says I agree with you, that כהנים Kohanim can't do
it. But the לויים מחרימין, Levi'im machrimim, they can be מחרים. machrim.
שאין חרמיהם שלהם, She'ein charmeihem shelahem, they don't keep it, so there,
why can't, of course they can do חרם, cherem, he says. אמר
רבי, Amar Rabbi, so says רבי, Rabbi, רבי's Rabbi's going to come
and make a compromise. נראים דברי רבי יהודה בקרקעות, Nirim divrei Rabbi
Yehuda bekarka'ot, I'm inclined to go like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who
says לויים Levi'im cannot do it by land. Why? שנאמר כי אחוזת
עולם היא להם, Shene'emar ki achuzat olam hi lahem, because when the
תורה Torah gives the, speaks about the ערי הלויים, arei HaLevi'im, it
says it is an eternal inheritance for them. So the word לעולם,
le'olam, אחוזת עולם
היא להם. achuzat olam hi lahem. So if they try to be
מחרים machrim their אחוזה, achuza, no no no, the תורה Torah says,
that has to stay yours, I'm not going to allow that חרם
cherem to take effect. Now of course you could ask other questions:
Can't they be מקידש? makdish? What if it's a לוי Levi that's
as opposed to חרם, cherem, what if the לוי Levi that's not
trying to be מחרים machrim his שדה אחוזה, sedei achuza, what if
he's trying to be מחרים machrim fields that he bought? Not his
שדה אחוזה, sedei achuza, not the ערי לויים. arei Levi'im. So you
know that's not so clear why we generalize it to all קרקע.
karka. But anyway he says so that at least I can accept,
their אחוזה, achuza, their cities are supposed to remain theirs. But ודברי
רבי שמעון, vedivrei Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says לויים Levi'im
can be
מחרים machrim במטלטלין, bemataltelin, that's by chattel. שאין חרמיהם שלהם, She'ein charmeihem
shelahem, that since they're not like כהנים, Kohanim, they don't get to
keep חרם cherem and it's chattel, they get to do it. So
by the כהנים Kohanim we have logic they're entitled to keep it,
that should be a stop of why it works. By the לויים
Levi'im we maybe have a logic by the, by their לוי Levi
cities. Okay, and now what we have to do is understand and
that's how רבי Rabbi sort of split his vote. Now we have
to understand the more extreme positions. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. ורבי יהודה, VeRabbi Yehuda, what would רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
say, who says even לויים Levi'im can't even be מחרים machrim מטלטלין,
metaltelin, chattel. בשלמא כהנים אין מחרימין, Bishlama Kohanim ein machrimim, I understand
that the כהנים, Kohanim, as says the גמרא, Gemara, I understand the
כהנים Kohanim can't be מחרים machrim שחרמיהם שלהם, shecharmeihem shelahem, they're entitled
to it. אלא לויים, Ella Levi'im, but when it comes to the
לוי, Levi, why can't they? בשלמא בקרקע, Bishlama bekarka, I understand land,
like רבי Rabbi told us, לא מחרימי, lo machrimi, they can't, דכתיב
כי אחוזת עולם היא להם. dechtiv ki achuzat olam hi lahem. אלא
מטלטלי ליחרמי? Ella metalteli leichremi? Okay, so רבי Rabbi made a very
good point, what you know, how do you, chattel, what's the logic?
So אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says if somebody is
מחרים machrim מכל אשר לו, mikol asher lo, from animals מבהמה mibeheima
ומשדה אחוזתו, umisedei achuzato, and from his field of inheritance. ומקיש מטלטלין
לקרקעות, Umakish metaltelin lekarka'ot, it links the two. So therefore it says
if you can be מחרים machrim your שדה אחוזה, sedei achuza, you
can be מחרים machrim your chattel. לויים Levi'im who can't be מחרים
machrim their שדה אחוזה sedei achuza because אחוזת עולם, achuzat olam, they're
not so that is agreed upon, they're not entitled to be מחרים
machrim the land from ערי לויים, arei Levi'im, so they're not in
the פרשה parsha to be מחרים machrim chattel as well. Those things
are linked. Okay, that's a nice דרשה. drasha. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
now let's understand the other extreme. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says
that לויים Levi'im can even be מחרים machrim קרקע. karka. How does
that work? בשלמא כהנים, Bishlama Kohanim, I understand that כהנים Kohanim can't,
כדאמרינן, ka'amrinan, it's what he himself says, because they're entitled to it.
אלא לויים, Ella Levi'im, but לויים Levi'im that they can, בשלמא מטלטלין,
Bishlama metaltelin, I understand chattel לאחרמי le'achremi דלא מקיש, delo makish,
because he doesn't link them to land. And he says fine, why
shouldn't לויים Levi'im be מחרים machrim chattel? אלא מקרקעי, Ella mikarkai, but
about land, especially if it's in the לויים Levi'im city, אמאי, amai,
why are they entitled to be מחרים? machrim? הא כתיב, Ha chtiv,
the פסוק pasuk says, אחוזת עולם היא להם, achuzat olam hi lahem,
it is an eternal inheritance, and we're assuming that that has to
mean that even חרם cherem doesn't work. Okay, even being מקיש makish
it doesn't work. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי מחרימין לא מחרימין
נמי דקאמר מטלטלי. Mai machrimim lo machrimim nami deka'amar metalteli. All right,
so this is actually quite fascinating. The גמרא Gemara feels that that
פסוק pasuk is so clear that it reinterprets the position of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. When רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that לויים Levi'im
can be מחרים, machrim, he never meant the land. He really just
meant that they can be, certainly not from their שדה אחוזה. sedei
achuza. He just meant their chattel. But the גמרא Gemara says, one
minute, right, right, so רבי Rabbi seems to be taking a compromise.
The גמרא Gemara says you're not taking a compromise, you're really just
saying is you're voting like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon if רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon himself admits by the land. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara says, one minute, ומהא דקתני סיפא, umeiha dekatana seifa, since the
end of the משנה Mishna says, אמר רבי נראין דברי רבי יהודה
בקרקע ודברי רבי שמעון במטלטלין, Amar Rabbi nir'in divrei Rabbi Yehuda bekarka
vedivrei Rabbi Shimon bemataltelin, that says, oh, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's right
by land, רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's right by by chattel. מכלל, Michlal,
the implication is דרבי שמעון בקרקע נמי קאמר, deRabbi Shimon bekarka nami
ka'amar, that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says even by קרקע karka they
can be מחרים, machrim, and you're just disagreeing with רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon on that point. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי קאמר, hachi
ka'amar, this is how you have to read the end of the
משנה. Mishna. אמר רבי נראין דברי רבי יהודה לרבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi
nir'in divrei Rabbi Yehuda leRabbi Shimon, when he's saying it seems like
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's right. Right by land and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is right by chattel. What he's really saying is it seems
to me that even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would not have disagreed
with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda when it came to land. So rather
than sort of giving a compromise position, he's giving an interpretation. He's
interpreting רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and saying רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon really
wouldn't have disagreed by land because the land there's a פסוק. pasuk.
Okay, בקרקעות אף רבי שמעון לא נחלק אלא במטלטלין. bi-karkaos af Reb
Shimon lo nechelak ela bi-metaltelin. Even רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position that
they can do it was only by chattel, אבל בקרקע מודה לו,
aval bi-karka modeh lo, he would agree by land. Okay, so this
is a re-interpretation of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Anyway, what we're saying
is that by land they can't be מחרים machrim because אחוזת עולם.
achuzas olam. And what I just the question I just asked what
put out there is number one, what if they're, what if on
the one hand it's not חרם, cherem, what if it's הקדש, hekdesh,
would we say the same thing? And number two, what if it
is not their שדה אחוזה? sadeh achuza? What if it's other types
of field? Okay, and even though we said not שדה מקנה sadeh
miknah because it's not permanent, let's say it's a שדה מקנה חוץ
לארץ. sadeh miknah chutz la-aretz. Let's say it's שדה מקנה sadeh miknah
when אין היובל נוהג, ein ha-yovel noheig, right? It would seem that
that should be able to work. It seems to only be limiting
the שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, the cities of הלוי. ha-Levi. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara is talking in more general terms. Let's take a
look now as we move further. אמר רבי חייא בר אבין, Amar
Rebbi Chiya bar Abin, החרים מטלטלין, hachrim metaltelin, נותן לכל כהן שירצה.
nosen le-chol kohen she-yirtzeh. So this was I think pretty implicit in
the arguments of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
they said since כהנים kohanim keep חרם, cherem, means that they're entitled
to keep it, so if they're entitled to keep it means that
who gets it means that you can choose which כהן kohen to
give it to. Right? Because if there was a specific rule which
כהן kohen got it, then even when you're מחרים machrim it, it's
not you're not in the position to receive it. Okay, so חרם
cherem you can choose who to give it to. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, כל
חרם בישראל לך יהיה. kol cherem bi-Yisrael lecha yiheyeh. This is a
פסוק pasuk in תורה Torah where it lists the gifts of the
כהנים kohanim and it says all חרם cherem will be to you.
So somehow לך, lecha, maybe it's in the singular, means that an
individual כהן kohen can be designated. So חרם cherem number one goes
to כהנים kohanim and number two, the person who made it חרם
cherem can designate which כהן kohen receives it. Sort of like you
have by תרומה ומעשר, terumah u-ma'aser, you can choose which כהן kohen
and לוי Levi to give your תרומה ומעשר. terumah u-ma'aser. שדותיו, Sadosav,
נותן לכהן שבאותו משמר. nosen le-kohen she-ba-oso mishmar. But this is interesting,
if you're מחרים machrim your fields, you don't get to designate. It
goes to the כהן kohen that is working in that משמר, mishmar,
in that weekly, as part of the weekly cycle, it's his it's
his week in the time when you were מקדיש makdish it. Where
do you get that from? שנאמר, She-ne'emar, כשדה החרם. ki-sadeh ha-cherem. Because
when the verse speaks about שדה אחוזה sadeh achuza going to the
כהנים, kohanim, it says it goes to the כהנים kohanim like a
שדה חרם sadeh cherem goes to the כהנים. kohanim. Okay, so what
does that tell me though? Well, first of all, remember that when
the fields go to the כהנים kohanim at the יובל, yovel, right?
We said before we're actually going to say it explicitly in the
גמרא, Gemara, which כהנים kohanim did they go to when the fields
go to the כהנים kohanim with the יובל? yovel? The כהנים kohanim
that are working in that משמר. mishmar. And here it's saying that
when I that it goes to the כהנים kohanim like a שדה
החרם. sadeh ha-cherem. So it suggests that in שדה החרם sadeh ha-cherem
as well, it does not go to a כהן kohen I designate
but it goes to a כהן kohen at the appropriate משמר. mishmar.
So for יובל yovel the appropriate משמר mishmar is the משמר mishmar
during יום כיפור Yom Kippur of the יובל. yovel. Here the appropriate
משמר mishmar is the משמר mishmar when I was מקדיש makdish or
מחרים machrim the field. כשדה החרם Ki-sadeh ha-cherem and so number one
that's just the context.
You remember which we did it.
Yeah, right exactly. And then we're going to make a גזירה שוה.
gezerah shavah. לכהן תהיה אחוזתו. La-kohen teheyeh achuzaso. To the כהן kohen
it will be. וגמר Ve-gammar לכהן לכהן la-kohen la-kohen מגזל הגר. mi-gezel
ha-ger. We make a גזירה שוה gezerah shavah from stealing from a
convert. The תורה Torah says that if a person steals, takes money
that doesn't belong to him and whatever or withholds something and then
he swears that he hasn't done it and he was lying, he
gives it back plus a fifth and he brings a special קרבן
korban called an אשם. asham. Now, let's say the person there is
nobody
there he doesn't have he's dead and there's no relative, what do
you do with the money? It says you give it to the
כהן. kohen. So the גמרא Gemara says what person doesn't have a
relative? Everybody all the Jewish people are related, they're all we're all
part of the same family. So it says it would be a
convert. And therefore there's no kids and there's no relative and so
on. So that's why it's called גזל הגר. gezel ha-ger. So there
we're going to say which כהן kohen gets the money? The כהן
kohen of the משמר mishmar when you come and bring it. So
here too the
גזירה שוה gezerah shavah of לכהן לכהן la-kohen la-kohen tells us that
it goes to the כהן kohen of the משמר. mishmar. Okay. והתם
מנלן? Ve-hasam minaylan? And how do you know there? דתניא, De-tanya, we
learned in a ברייתא. beraisa. לה' לכהן. Lashem la-kohen. It says the
אשם asham which is returned to God to the כהן. kohen. So
the קרבן korban and the money that goes to God to the
כהן. kohen. So קנאו השם, keno Hashem, God has taken possession of
this money, וקנסתו לכהן שבאותו משמר, u-kinnasto le-kohen she-ba-oso mishmar, and has
awarded it to the כהן kohen of that משמר. mishmar. Now, which
one? It's going to seem like it's the one actually who you
choose to do your
קרבן. korban. אתה אומר לכהן שבאותו משמר או אינו אלא לכל כהן
שירצה? Atta omer le-kohen she-ba-oso mishmar o eino ela le-chol kohen she-yirtzeh?
Maybe I can designate a
כהן? kohen? כשהוא אומר, Ke-she-hu omer, מלבד איל הכפורים אשר יכפר בו
עליו, mi-levad eil ha-kippurim asher yechaper bo alav, that you bring back
this money plus the ram of atonement, so and you bring the
money and this ram together, so and this is the אשם גזילות,
asham gezeilos, it's a special אשם, asham, הרי כהן שבאותו משמר כתוב
מדבר. harei kohen she-ba-oso mishmar kasuv medaber. So the same way, so
it's all one package. So the same way the כהן kohen who's
working that week brings it, he's also the כהן kohen who receives
it. So it seems like it is a specific כהן, kohen, not
divided by the כהנים, kohanim, but it's the כהן. kohen. The כהן
Kohen who is doing the עבודה. Avodah. But anyway, the לכהן לכהן
Lakohen Lakohen גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah tells us that when it's fields
as well, it is the כהנים Kohanim during the משמר mishmar when
I sanctified it. And I also think as I said that the
even stronger comparison is that the exact comparison in the פסוקים pesukim
is the fields that are going back in the יובל Yovel to
the כהנים. Kohanim. And those are going to the כהנים Kohanim the
יובל Yovel and this one as well. And now we're going to
keep on talking about which כהנים Kohanim get what and go to
the points that we've mentioned before. Let's really make a push to
get to the משנה. Mishna. Okay, שדה היוצא לכהנים ביובל, Sadeh hayotzei
lakohanim baYovel, this is what we've been talking about for the last
week. When the fields go to the כהנים Kohanim in the יובל,
Yovel, fields that were sanctified, somebody else redeemed it and now it
goes to the כהנים. Kohanim. Which כהן Kohen gets it? ניתנת למשמר
שפגע בו יובל. Nitnat lamishmar shepaga bo Yovel. The משמר mishmar in
which the יובל, Yovel, assume to mean יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, obviously
not the whole year, assume to mean יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, occurred.
So that is the משמר mishmar that you want to be in,
okay? It's different each fifty years, but that's the one that all
the כהנים Kohanim of that week divide all the fields that were
sanctified and redeemed by other fields. Okay, איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. Now
again, it's not explicit in the פסוקים, pesukim, that's just, it's interesting
the גמרא Gemara doesn't say מנא הני מילי. mena hanei milei. We're
just assuming that that's gotta be the case. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu,
they asked the question: פגע בו בשבת מאי? paga bo beShabbos mai?
Let's say יום כיפור Yom Kippur fell out on שבת. Shabbos. So
there are two משמרות mishmarot that work on שבת. Shabbos. שבת Shabbos
was the switch-over day. So which משמר mishmar gets it? The one
that was working the past week or the following week? So אמר
רבי חייא בר אמי משמיה דחופנא, Amar Rabi Chiya bar Ami mishmei
deChofna, ניתנת למשמר היוצא. Nitnat lamishmar hayotzei. You give it to the
משמר mishmar that's leaving, meaning the one that had been working. You
know, you might say anyway that they have already a, what do
you call it, not seniority, but whatever. I mean they were there
first. But the גמרא's Gemara actually going to say another logic, which
is that although the יובל Yovel really kicks in on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, the year began on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So the,
so now although the ones that, although they weren't there ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah, right, because it's ten days earlier, whatever, but nevertheless they
were there already with part of the יובל Yovel and they had
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so that gives them a little extra weight.
Okay, they were there closer to the beginning. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: תניא נמי הכי, וחסמיה לי. Tanya nami hachi vechasmiyei
lei, אמר רב יצחק בר אבדימי, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, תניא
נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi, וחסמיה לי, vechasmiyei lei. נמצאת אתה אומר:
nimtzet ata omer: אחד יובל ואחד שביעית, echad Yovel ve'echad Shevi'is, whether
it's if you have a שמיטה Shemitah like in a normal case
it's a שמיטה Shemitah year and then a יובל Yovel year, right?
Forty-nine and then a יובל Yovel year. So both of them משמיטין
כאחד, mashmitin ke'echad, they have their effect on the same day to
cause things to be annulled or reversed. What means, what does that
mean? שמיטה, Shemitah, what does it reverse? It annuls debts. It reverses
as it were the indebtedness. יובל Yovel reverses the sense about the
slaves and the land going back. Says it all happens on the
same day essentially. Why? Because the annulment of debts happens at the
very end of שמיטה. Shemitah. The freeing of slaves and the going
back of the fields happens at the beginning of יובל. Yovel. So
the beginning of יובל Yovel and the end of שמיטה Shemitah are
basically the move from the last day of אלול Elul in the
שמיטה Shemitah to ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. And in that last second
and that second of transition
the debts get annulled from שמיטה Shemitah and the reversals happen, you
know, in the יובל. Yovel. Assuming that it happens on ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah the יובל, Yovel, not יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, so
let's take a look.
They all happen at the same time אלא שהיובל בתחלתו ela shehaYovel
bit-chilato but the יובל Yovel is at the beginning of it והשמיטה
בסופה vehaShemitah besofah and the שמיטה Shemitah is at the end. So
the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה, aderaba, what do you mean except that?
משום הכי הוי, mishum hachi havei, that's why it's the same day.
So the גמרא Gemara says okay אימא מפני שהיובל, eima mipnei shehaYovel,
fine, say because. So that's what it means. It happens on the
same day because since the יובל Yovel is the שמיטה Shemitah is
the end, the annulment of debt, and the יובל Yovel is the
beginning, it all actually happens at the same second. So the גמרא
Gemara says בשלמא שביעית בסופה, bishlama shevi'is besofah, I understand why שמיטה
Shemitah annuls at the end דכתיב מקץ שבע שנים תעשה שמיטה, dechtiv
miketz sheva shanim ta'aseh shemitah, at the end of seven years you
shall
annul. אלא יובל בתחלתו, Ela Yovel bit-chilato, what do you mean יובל's
Yovel the beginning? It's ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? ביום הכיפורים הוא, Beyom
haKippurim hu, it's on יום כיפור! Yom Kippur! דכתיב ביום הכפורים תעבירו
שופר בכל ארצכם, dechtiv beyom haKippurim ta'aviru shofar bechol artzechem, have the
שופר shofar blast. הא מני רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא היא, Ha meni Rabi Yishmael beno shel Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka
hi, this is רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael the son of רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka דאמר מראש השנה הוא דחייל יובל,
de'amar meRosh Hashanah hu dechayal Yovel, that the effect begins on ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. The גמרא Gemara explains this in מסכת ראש השנה.
Masechet Rosh Hashanah. Well, not that you right, but it also says
you cannot enslave the slaves, but they don't yet go free. So
on the one hand your right to the slaves, your right has
stopped on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, but their freedom is held off
until יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So because it begins on ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah, I don't know, because it begins on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah so in a certain way it all happens at the same
second. Now how is it relevant for our discussion? It's only relevant
for our discussion to say that at least there's an opinion and
maybe that there's weight to the period before ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
so therefore the משמר mishmar that was that was already there first
is the one that has greater weight and therefore is the one
that gets it, even though they weren't there for ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah itself. Okay, let's just end up.
שמע חזקיה בר בלוטי, Shama Chizkiyah bar Biloti, so חזקיה בר בלוטי
Chizkiyah bar Biloti over here was, heard this, ואזל אמר קמיה דרבי
אבהו, ve'azal amar kamei deRabi Abbahu, he told this over to רבי
אבהו, Rabi Abbahu, this idea. So רבי אבהו Rabi Abbahu says that
לא קש מטלטלי לקרקע, la kash mataltalei lekarka, I don't get it
he says. When you say חרם, cherem, now we're going way back
to the earlier point, that the חרם cherem of a כהן Kohen
when it's chattel you designate and when it's land it goes to
the כהנים Kohanim of the משמר. mishmar. How can you split chattel
and land? The פסוק pasuk connects them all. It says whether whatever
you sanctify, your chattel, your land, etc., so it should all be
the same. So he says, so the answer's obvious. He says לא
תנאי la tannai דמקיש de-makkish ודלא מקיש. u-dela makkish. תנא
דלא מקישינא. tanna de-la makkishina. We just got through saying that there's
a question, right, remember in the משנה mishnah about the לויים Leviim
and so on, do you connect the chattel to the land or
not? So this position doesn't connect the chattel to the land. You
don't have to buy into the fact that they're connected. So therefore
you can say that when you מחרים machrim chattel, you can designate
the כהן, kohen, and when you're מחרים machrim your שדה אחוזה, sedeh
achuzah, it goes to the כהנים kohanim of the משמר. mishmar. But
now we've officially said what we've been implying all along, which is
that the כהנים kohanim of the משמר mishmar on יובל Yovel are
the ones that get the land that returns. And גמרא Gemara we
will talk about that, this question of who really gets the חרם.
cherem. We're assuming it's the כהנים, kohanim, but this will be more
discussed.